

# Hoseung Cha

Ph.D. · POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER · BIOSIGNAL/DATA SCIENTIS

222, Wangsimni-ro 222, Seongdong-gu, Seoul, 04763, SOUTH KOREA

□ (+82) 10-4037-2405 | ■ hoseungcha@gmail.com | 🏕 hs-cha.github.io | 🖸 hs-cha | 🛅 hoseungcha

"The first step is to establish that something is possible; then probability will occur."

# **Summary**

Ph.D @ Hanyang university. 7+ years of experience analyzing in biosignal/data such as electroenchpahlogram (EEG), electromyogram (EMG), electrooculogram (EOG), etc. My research topics include myoelectric control, brain-computer interfacing, and computational neuroscience. Skilled in the application of machine learning or deep learning algorithms using Matlab and Python. I have developed various real-time biosignal-based applications such as 1) facial expression recognition system based on EMG [Click], 2) silent speech recognition system based on EMG [Click], 4) Triple blink detection system based on EOG [Click], etc.

# **Experiences**

#### Bio-Interfaced Translational Nanoengineering Group @ Georgia Tech

Atlanta, GA, USA

(Projected) March 2021 - Jan 2022

(PROJECTED) POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER CANDIDATE

#### Computational Neuroengineering Lab @ Hanyang University

Seoul, S.Korea

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Sep 2020 - Dec 2020

• Prof. Chang-Hwan Im's Lab [Click]

• Prof. Woon-Hong Yeo's Lab [Click]

#### **Computational Neuroengineering Lab @ Hanyang University**

Seoul, S.Korea

POSTGRADUATE RESEARCHER

Sep 2015 - Feb 2016

• Prof. Chang-Hwan Im's Lab [Click]

#### **Computational Neuroengineering Lab @ Hanyang University**

Seoul, S.Korea

Undergraduate Researcher

Mar 2013 - Aug 2013

• Prof. Chang-Hwan Im's Lab [Click]

## **Education**

Hanyang University Seoul, S.Korea

Ph.D. IN BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING, GPA: 98.9/100

Mar 2016 - Aug 2020

• Thesis: Development of Face-Machine Interfaces Using Facial Electromyogram for Interactive Virtual Reality Applications

Hanyang University Seoul, S.Korea

M.S. IN BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING, GPA: 98.2/100

Sep 2013 - Aug 2015

• Thesis: Development of a transient visual evoked potential (tVEP)-based brain switch system [Click]

Yonsei University Wonju, S.Korea Wonju, S.Korea

B.S. IN BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING, GPA: 95/100

Mar 2008 - Aug 2013

• Received four scholarships for excellence in grades in 2009 and 2010 (total four semesters)

# Honors & Awards\_

2019	Best Paper Award, 55th Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering [Click]	Incheon, S. Korea
2019	Best Poster Paper Award, 54th Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering [Click]	Yeosu, S. Korea
2018	Young Investigator Award, SMIT2018-IBEC2018 Joint Conference [Click]	Seoul, S. Korea
2018	Young Investigator Travel Award, SMIT2018-IBEC2018 Joint Conference [Click]	Seoul, S. Korea
2016	Best Poster Award, International Biomedical Engineering Conference [Click]	Seoul, S. Korea
2015	Excellence Poster Paper Award, 50th Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering [Click]	Daegu, S. Korea
2010	Highest honor (top 1% students for 2010 spring semester), Yonsei University	Wonju, S.Korea

#### **PUBLISHED**

11. **Ho-Seung Cha**, Seong-Jun Choi, and Chang-Hwan Im\*, Real-time Recognition of Facial Expressions using Facial Electromyograms Recorded around the Eyes for Social Virtual Reality Applications

IEEE Access, vol. 8, pp. 62065-62075, Mar. 2020. [Link]

10. **Ho-Seung Cha**, Chang-Hee Han, and Chang-Hwan Im\*, Prediction of Individual User's Dynamic Ranges of EEG Features from Resting-State EEG Data for Evaluating Their Suitability for Passive Brain–Computer Interface Applications

Sensors, vol. 20(4), pp. 988, Feb. 2020. [Link]

9. Seonghun Park, **Ho-Seung Cha**, and Chang-Hwan Im\*, Development of an Online Home Appliance Control System Using Augmented Reality and an SSVEP-Based Brain–Computer Interface

IEEE Access, vol. 7, pp. 163604-163614, Nov. 2019. [Link]

8. Do Yeon Kim, Jinuk Kwon, Joo-Young Kim, **Ho-Seung Cha**, Yong-Wook Kim, In Young Kim, and Chang-Hwan Im\*, New Method for Pure-Tone Audiometry Using Electrooculogram: A Proof-of-Concept Study

Sensors, vol. 18, Art.No.3651, Oct. 2018. [Link]

7. Jeong-Hwan Lim, Yong-Wook Kim, Jun-Hak Lee, Kwang-Ok An, Han-Jeong Hwang, **Ho-Seung Cha**, Chang-Hee Han, and Chang-Hwan Im, An emergency call system for patients in locked-in state using an SSVEP-based brain switch

Psychophysiology, vol. 54, pp. 1632-1634, May 2017. [Link]

6. Han-Jeong Hwang, Chang-Hee Han, Jeong-Hwan Lim, Yong-Wook Kim, Soo-In Choi, Kwang-Ok An, Jun-Hak Lee, Ho-Seung Cha, Seung Hyun Kim, and Chang-Hwan Im\*, Clinical Feasibility of Brain-Computer Interface Based on Steady-State Visual Evoked Potential in Patients with Locked-in Syndrome: Case Studies

Psychophysiology, vol. 54, pp. 444-451, Dec. 2016. [Link]

5. Won-Du Chang, **Ho-Seung Cha**, Do Yeon Kim, Seung Hyun Kim, Chang-Hwan Im\*, Development of an electrooculogram-based eye-computer interface for communication of individuals with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis

Journal of NeuroEngineering and Rehabilitation, vol. 14, Art. ID 89, Sep. 2017. [Link]

4. Won-Du Chang, **Ho-Seung Cha**, Chany Lee, Hoon-Chul Kang, and Chang-Hwan Im\*, Automatic Identification of Interictal Epileptiform Discharges in Secondary Generalized Epilepsy

Computational and Mathematical Methods in Medicine, vol. 2016, Art. ID 8701973, Jun. 2016. [Link]

3. Won-Du Chang, **Ho-Seung Cha**, Kiwoong Kim, Chang-Hwan Im\*, Detection of eye blink artifacts from single prefrontal channel electroencephalogram

Sensors, vol. 124, pp. 19-30, Feb. 2016. [Link]

2. Won-Du Chang, **Ho-Seung Cha**, Chang-Hwan Im\*, Removing the Interdependency between Horizontal and Vertical Eye-Movement Components in Electrooculograms

Sensors, vol. 16(2), pp. 227, Feb. 2016. [Link]

1. Ho-Seung Cha, Won-Du Chang, YoungSeok Shin, and Chang-Hwan Im\*, EEG-based Neurocinematics: Challenges and Prospects

Brain-Computer Interfaces, vol. 2(4), pp. 186-192, Feb. 2016. [Link]

#### SUBMITTED

2. **Ho-Seung Cha** and Chang-Hwan Im\*, Performance Enhancement of Facial Electromyogram-based Facial-expression Recognition for Social Virtual Reality Applications Using Linear Discriminant Analysis Adaptation

Virtual Reality, Submitted

1. **Ho-Seung Cha**, Won-Du Chang, and Chang-Hwan Im\*, Deep-Learning-Based Real-Time Silent Speech Recognition using Facial Electromyogram Recorded Around Eyes for Hands-Free Interfacing in Virtual Reality Environment

IEEE Transactions on Emerging Topics in Computing, Under review

#### INTERNATIONAL

- 14. **Ho-Seung Cha**, Seongjun Choi, and Chang-Hwan Im, Real-Time Electromyogram-Based Facial Expression Recognition Using Riemannian Geometry Features for VR Applications
  - 41st International Conference of the IEEE EMBS, Berlin, Germany, July 26, 2019
- 13. Seong-Jun Choi, **Ho-Seung Cha**, and Chang-Hwan Im\*, Emotion Inference Method Using Facial EMG-based Facial Expression Recognition Technology for VR Applications
  - SMIT2018-IBEC2018 Joint Conference, Seoul, South Korea, November 9, 2018.
- 12. **Ho-Seung Cha** and Chang-Hwan Im\*, New Strategy for Minimizing Training Time In EMG-Based Facial Expression Recognition for Virtual Reality Applications
  - SMIT2018-IBEC2018 Joint Conference, Seoul, South Korea, November 9, 2018.
- 11. Seongjun Choi, **Ho-Seung Cha**, and Chang-Hwan Im, User Authentication for Virtual Reality Applications Based on Facial EMG Induced by Facial Expression Changes
  - 40th International Conference of the IEEE EMBS, Honolulu, USA, July 18, 2018
- 10. **Ho-Seung Cha** and Chang-Hwan Im, Prediction of individual user's suitability for passive BCI applications using short resting EEG recordings
  - 7th International BCI Meeting, Pacific Grove, California, USA, May 22, 2018
- 9. Ho-Seung Cha, Won-Du Chang and Chang-Hwan Im, Real-time Recognition of Lip Gestures Based on Facial EMG
  - 3rd Annual International Biomedical Engineering Conference, Seoul, Korea, November 11, 2016
- 8. Ho-Seung Cha, Won-Du Chang and Chang-Hwan Im, A Real-Time Lip Gesture Recognition System using Facial EMG
  - 38th Annual International Conference of the IEEE EMBS, Orlando, Florida, USA, August 19, 2016
- 7. Won-Du Chang, **Ho-Seung Cha**, and Chang-Hwan Im, Improved Electrooculogram-based Eye-writing Recognition Using a New Feature Extraction Method
  - 2nd Annual International Biomedical Engineering Conference, Gyeongju, Korea, November 12, 2015
- 6. **Ho-Seung Cha** and Won-Du Chang, Young-Seok Shin, Dongpyo Jang and Chang-Hwan Im, EEG-Based Neurocinematics: Potential Brain Indices for Rating Films
  - 37th Annual International Conference of the IEEE EMBS, Milano, Italy, Aug 25 29, 2015
- 5. Jeong-Hwan Lim, Yong-Wook Kim, Chang-Hee Han, **Ho-Seung Cha**, and Chang-Hwan Im, An Emergency Call System for Patients with Severe ALS Using Less-Stimulating SSVEP-Based Brain Switch
  - 37th Annual International Conference of the IEEE EMBS, Milano, Italy, Aug 2015
- 4. Won-Du Chang, **Ho-Seung Cha** and Chang-Hwan Im Kang, and Chang-Hwan Im\*, A New Method for Detecting Eye-Blink Artifacts from a single-Channel Electroencephalogram
  - 36th Annual International Conference of the IEEE EMBS, Chicago, Illinois USA, Aug 2014
- 3. Won-Du Chang, **Ho-Seung Cha**, and Chang-Hwan Im\*, Enhanced Template Matching Using Dynamic Positional Warping for Pattern Recognition in Electroencephalogram
  - 36th Annual International Conference of the IEEE EMBS, Chicago, Illinois USA, August 2014
- 2. Jeong-Hwan Lim, Jun-Hak Lee, Yong-Wook Kim, Han Choi, Chang-Hee Han, **Ho-Seung Cha**, and Chang-Hwan Im\*, Implementation of a Steady State Visual Evoked Potential (SSVEP)-Based Online Brain-Switch System Using a Chromatic Stimulus
  - 36th Annual International Conference of the IEEE EMBS, Chicago, Illinois USA, Aug 2014.
- 1. **Ho-Seung Cha**, Jeong-Hwan Lim, Chang-Hee Han, Han-Jeong Hwang, Won-Du Chang and Chang-Hwan Im\*, A Transient Visual Evoked Potential (tVEP)-based Brain Switch System

## DOMESTIC (S. KOREA)

- 13. **Ho-Seung Cha** and Chang-Hwan Im, Development of Silent Speech Recognition System Based on Facial Electromyogram Recorded around Eyes for Hands-free Interactions in Virtual Environments
  - Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering (KOSOMBE), Inchon, Nov 7, 2019
- 12. Kang-min Choi, **Ho-Seung Cha**, and Chang-Hwan Im, Real-time Eye Gaze Tracking Method Using Electrooculogram Signals Recorded around Eyes in Virtual Environments
  - Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering (KOSOMBE), Inchon, Nov 7, 2019
- 11. Jung-Hwan Kim, **Ho-Seung Cha**, Seoungjae Lee, Chuljin Park, In Young Kim, Se-Keun Park, and Chang-Hwan Im, Development of Dyslexia Diagnosis System Using Electrooculogram: a Proof-of-concept Study
  - Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering (KOSOMBE), Inchon, Nov 7, 2019
- 10. Seong-Jun Choi, Chunghwan Kim, **Ho-Seung Cha**, and Chang-Hwan Im, Development of Facial Motion Capture Technology Based on Facial Electromyogram Using Deep Learning
  - Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering (KOSOMBE), Inchon, Nov 7, 2019
- 9. **Ho-Seung Cha**, and Chang-Hwan Im, Development of Avatar Expressing Emotions in Real Time Using Facial Electromyogram-based Facial Expression in Virtual Environment
  - Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering (KOSOMBE), Yeosu, May 9, 2019
- 8. **Ho-Seung Cha**, Seong-Jun Choi, Hodam Kim, and Chang-Hwan Im, Performance Comparison of Classification Techniques for the Facial Expression Recognition Based on Surface EMG
  - Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering (KOSOMBE), Chenbuk university, Cheonbuk, Nov 11 2017
- 7. **Ho-Seung Cha**, Won-Du Chang, Young Seok Shin, Dong Pyo Jang, and Chang-Hwan Im, Neurocinematics: Development of Indices of Evaluating Cinematic Using EEG
  - Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering (KOSOMBE), Pusan, May 13, 2016
- 6. Jeong-Hwan Lim, Yong-Wook Kim, **Ho-Seung Cha**, Chang-Hee Han, and Chang-Hwan Im, An Emergency Call System for Patients with Severe ALS Using Less-Stimulating SSVEP-Based Brain Switch
  - Korean Society for Computational Neuroscience, Seoul, August 19, 2015
- 5. **Ho-Seung Cha**, JongYoep Lim, Da-sol Jeon, Won-Du Chang, and Chang-Hwan Im, Electrooculogram-based Real-time Digit Input System *Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering (KOSOMBE)*, Daegu, S. Korea, May 8, 2015
- 4. Jeong-Hwan Lim, Yong-Wook Kim, Jun-Hak Lee, **Ho-Seung Cha**, and Chang-Hwan Im, Implementation of a Steady State Visual Evoked Potential-based "Less Stimulating" Brain Switch System Using a Chromatic Stimulus
  - Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering (KOSOMBE), Daegu, May 8, 2015
- 3. **Ho-Seung Cha**, Jeong-Hwan Lim, Han-Jeong Hwang, Chang-Hee Han, and Chang-Hwan Im, Development of the Brain Switch System Using CTVEP
  - Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering (KOSOMBE), Osong, May 9, 2014
- 2. Won-Du Chang, **Ho-Seung Cha**, and Chang-Hwan Im, A Study on Automatic Detection of Spikes from a Single-Channel Electroencephalogram
  - Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering (KOSOMBE), Osong, May 9, 2014
- 1. **Ho-Seung Cha**, Jeong-Hwan Lim, Han-Jeong Hwang, Chang-Hee Han, and Chang-Hwan Im, Development of a VEP-based brain switch system
  - Korean Society of Medical & Biological Engineering (KOSOMBE), Inchon, Nov 8, 2013

#### INTERNATIONAL

 Chang-Hwan Im, Ho-Seung Cha, Seong-Jun Choi, Electronic Device, Avatar Facial Expression System and Controlling Method Thereof Filed, US 16/534,579, Aug 2019. [Link]

## DOMESTIC (S. KOREA)

8. Chang-Hwan Im and **Ho-Seung Cha**, Apparatus and Method for User Authentication Using Facial EMG by Measuring Changes of Facial Expression of HMD User

Issued, KR 1020944880000, Mar 2020. [Link]

7. Chang-Hwan Im and Ho-Seung Cha, Emotion Recognition Method and Device Using Electromyogram Signal

Issued, KR 10-2018-0080953, Jan 2020. [Link]

6. Won-Du Chang, Chang-Hwan Im, **Ho-Seung Cha**, Asynchronous Eye-Character Recognition Method and Apparatus Using Electromyogram Data

Issued, KR 10-2019-0124660, vol. 54, pp. 1632-1634, Oct 2019. [Link]

5. Chang-Hwan Im, Kang-Min Choi, **Ho-Seung Cha**, Method for Tracking Eye of HMD User and HMD for Tracking Eye of User

Issued, KR 10-2019-0117185, Sep 2019. [Link]

4. Chang-Hwan Im, **Ho-Seung Cha**, Seong-Jun Choi, Learning Method and Apparatus for Facial Expression Recognition, Facial Expression Recognition Method Using Electromyogram Data

Filed, KR 10-2018-0031888, Mar 2018. [Link]

3. Won-Du Chang, Chang-Hwan Im, **Ho-Seung Cha**, Kwang-Ryeol Lee, Method and System for Recognition of Eye-Character based on Tracking Technique of Electro Oculogram Gaze

Issued, KR 10-2016-0117716, Jun 2017. [Link]

2. Chang-Hwan Im, Won-Du Chang, **Ho-Seung Cha**, System and method for detecting spikes whose widths are within a certain range in time-series data

Issued, KR 10-2014-0058590, Dec 2015. [Link]

1. **Ho-Seung Cha**, Chang-Hwan Im, Jeong-Hwan Lim, Han-Jeong Hwang, Chang-Hee Han, Won-Du Chang, Method and apparatus for generating signals using transient visual evoked potential

Issued, KR 10-2013-0168546, vol. 2(4), Jul 2015. [Link]

## Software \_

3. Facial electromyogram-based facial expression recognition system

C-2018-036477, Dec 2018. [Click]

2. F-avatar

C-2018-036476, Dec 2018. [Click]

1. Bio-Control

C-2018-030968, Nov 2018. [Click]

## Press

3. VR Avatars Copy Your Facial Expressions. When you smile, they smile with you

News-H, Jan 2019. [Link (Korean)] [Link (English)]

2. VR Avatar looks exactly like me!

Dong-A Ilbo, Dec 2018. [Link] [Click to see the article capture]

1. Why don't we rate movie using "brainwave indices"?

DongaScience, Dec 2014 [Link]

# **Projects**

#### RESEARCH PROJECTS

#### Recognizing Facial Expressions Based on Facial Electromyogram for Interactive VR **Applications**

Samsung Science & Technology Foundation @ Samsung Electronics

Sep 2017 - Aug 2020

PARTICIPATING RESEARCHER

- PI: Prof. Chang-Hwan Im
- develop real-time facial expression recognition system [Click to see the paper] [Click to see the video]

## Development of Non-invasive Integrated BCI SW Platform To Control Home Appliance and External Devices By User's Thought Via AR/VR Interface

PARTICIPATING RESEARCHER

- PI: Prof. Chang-Hwan Im
- develop emotion recognition system using facial electromyogram [Click to see the patent]

Korea Institute of Science and Technology (KIST)

Apr 2017 - Dec 2023

## Development of Multimodal Brain-Machine Inference System Based on User Intent Recognition

PARTICIPATING RESEARCHER

- PI: Prof. Inyoung Kim
- develop EEG indices for predicting user's BCI application suitability [Click to see the paper]

Information & Communication Technology Promotion (IITP)

May 2013 - Feb 2017

#### **Development of Bio-Signal Analysis Algorithm for Wearable Devices**

PARTICIPATING RESEARCHER

- PI: Prof. Chang-Hwan Im
- develop an eye-gaze direction detection system using electrooculogram
- develop an silent speech recognition system using electromyogram
- contribute C-lab team's spin-off (Linkface)[Click to see the article]

# Samsung Electronics

Oct 2016 - Dec 2016

#### Development of Eye Tracking Source Technology Based on Electrooculogram for HCI **Application**

PARTICIPATING RESEARCHER

- · PI: Prof. Won-Du Chang
- design and conduct experiments for recording electrooculogram signals [Click to see the paper]
- conduct EEG data analysis and abnormal EEG data/pattern classification of epilepsy patients

## National Research Foundation (NRF)

May 2015 - Apr 2017

#### Development of real-time bio-signal-based cultural content evaluation technology focused on large customers

PARTICIPATING RESEARCHER

- · PI: Prof. Dong pyo Jang
- develop EEG indices for evaluating cinematics [Click to see the paper] [Click to see the article]

# Korea Institute of Industrial Technology (KITECH)

May 2013 - Feb 2016

## Development of original technologies for brain-computer interface based on the spatiotemporospectral analysis of brain activity patterns

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- PI: Prof. Won-Du Chang
- develop transient visual evoked potential (tVER)-based brain switch system[click to see the patent]

## Ministry of Science, ICT and Future Plannina

Oct 2013 - July 2014

#### Personal Projects

#### Personal homepage

Sep 2020 -ADMINISTRATOR

create personal homepage using GitHub page [Click]

**DEVELOPER** Sep 2010 - Dec 2010

• visual programming class project (A+) @ Yonsei University.

# Skills\_

**Data analysis experiences** Bio-electric signals (EEG/EMG/EOG) · GSR · 3D motion data · Images

**Research techniques** Machine learning · Deep learning · Time-frequency signal analysis · Real-time Data Analysis

**Programming** Matlab · Python · C++/C

Web/Media Adobe premiere
Language Korean · English

# References\_

Chang-Hwan Im (Ph.D.)

Seoul, S. Korea

PROFESSOR, CHAIR | DEPARTMENT OF BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING @ HANYANG UNIVERSITY

Office: +82-2-2220-2322E-mail: ich@hanyang.ac.kr

• Homapage [Click]

Won-Du Chang (Ph.D.)

Pusan, S. Korea

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR | DEPARTMENT OF COMPUTER ENGINEERING @ PUKYONG NATIONAL UNIVERSITY

Office: +82-51-629-6246e-mail: chang@pknu.ac.kr

• Homepage [Click]

YoungJin Jung (Ph.D.)

Pusan, S. Korea

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR | DEPARTMENT OF RADIOLOGICAL SCIENCE AT HEALTH SCIENCE DIVISION @ DONGSEO UNIVERSITY

• Tell: +82-51-320-2871

• E-mail: microbme@dongseo.ac.kr

• Homepage [Click]